so this is the first ever suta that the
Buddha gave it's the setting in motion
of the wheel of the
dma thus have I heard on one occasion
the blessed one was dwelling at barasi
in the Deer Park at isipatana there the
blessed one addressed the buus of the
group of five thus buus these two sides
should not be followed by one who has
gone forth into homelessness what two
the pursuit of sensual happiness and
sensual Pleasures which is low vulgar
the way of
worldlings inoble
unbeneficial and the pursuit of self
ification which is painful inoble
unbeneficial without veering towards
either of these sides the tagata has
awakened to the middle way which gives
rise to wisdom which give gives rise to
knowledge which leads to peace to direct
knowledge to Enlightenment to
Nana and what because is that middle way
awakened to by the which gives rise to
vision and which leads to Nana it is
this Noble hateful path that is Right
View right intention right speech right
action right livelihood right effort
right recollection right
composure this because is that middle
way awakened to by the tagata which
gives rise to Vision to knowledge to
Beast to direct knowledge to
Enlightenment to so what
so what
is the difference
between the middle way that the Buddha
discovered and
and
aestheticism and Indulgence
because back in the day some people
accused the Buddha of both they would
accuse them of being an aesthetic of
being a
denialist and some others would accuse
them of
being um
indulgent so what is it that really distinguish is
so what is it that really distinguish is
the middle
way those two
sides see body has not self see seeing
body as not
self like indulging in sensual pleasures
obviously takes
body as as body as a central reference
point and the and the self modification
as well so seeing that that body is not
self seems to me is is one part of the S
the middleway well yeah but that would be
middleway well yeah but that would be
kind
of farther down the development like
let's say somebody is starting out
and the Buddha tells them so okay how do
you you know the classic classic formula
about somebody hearing the dhama it says
that they go forth and then they take on
these precepts which is um basically the
eight precepts including
celibacy uh sense restraint uh
moderation and
eating um so seclusion
so many people would say that those
things are a form of
aestheticism like not
uh yeah not eating in the
afternoon um not delighting in Company Living away
um not delighting in Company Living away
from others they would say that that is
an
extreme path of aestheticism mhm and
then other other people who kind of go
further into who are proper Aesthetics
they would say well the fact that you
eat in the morning you eat only once but
you eat anything kind of you eat like
delicious food sometimes and uh or they
would say
well um when it's cold you use heating
and when it's when it's hot you use fans
or air conditioner therefore you're not
like atics would accuse uh people who
are practicing the middle way
from being indulgent so like why is why
is uh none of those criticisms
valid uh like why is the middle way
genuinely above those two what is it
that distinguishes
distinguishes
them without like just from that from a
beginner's point of view not necessarily
like later on because it's saying
they're like the the the Noble aold Path
m
like knowing the body is not self and
and all that stuff that would kind of
um you don't start with that let's put
it that way I see yeah
mhm well to some degree you could
um put it
like a begin's point like you might
recognize to some degree the
unsatisfactory nature of indulging in
Pleasures um I guess for someone who has
um what you call it
practiced like more strict aestheticism
they might be able to
recognize that uh that's
not yes doesn't bring sa well
satisfaction it doesn't um how
kind of feeds itself so to say so the
more you do it the more you need to do
it kind of becom dependent on it on that
practice whatever it is for your uh
piece so to say whether it's indulging
in sexual pleasures or indulging
in like self notification and so you're
saying like Indulgence in self
modification well it's also a form of
indulgence basically yeah so like but
what how do you know whether cuz
externally it might look very similar
especially to someone who isn't kind of
uh Who had who doesn't have experience
with the practice themselves one person
who is
practicing Indulgence in self
mortification and the person who is just
practicing renunciation which you could
say is the middle way um like what would
be the distinguishing uh aspect that
they can know for
themselves um not necessarily by what
others are are kind
judging what the kind of state of mind
or the intention behind doing
it so what what would be the intention
behind someone who's practicing self
mortification like how is it
U well yeah essentially it's rooted in
how you feel Bas so trying to
trying to change the feeling in such a
way that pleases you basically whether
it's Pleasant or
painful yeah wanting to get rid of
things yeah is an attitude that is
behind the self modification and wanting
to get things is an attitude behind
sensuality and they both miss the
point and in fact the attitude behind
like self modification you're getting
rid of things because you also want to
get something yeah but not not in the
same uh course level as sensual
Pleasures but you still want to get kind
of um whatever your idea of what
enlightenment is yeah you're chasing
after it through this through this
practice yeah and that's why like one
very strong sign of somebody who's
practicing self mortification is that if
they are um
are um
if they're suddenly not able to do those
practices that they're holding on to as
as a as a means of of um supposedly
freeing themselves from suffering they
will suffer so like those
practices they even if they don't depend
on the world anymore like they don't
depend on of course sights sounds smells
taste touches their emotional dependence
is is on this practice now yeah so like
if if they don't do it they would
suffer pretty much the same as somebody
who is dependent on sense objects yeah
so it's just
that generally it is harder to be forced
to give up those practices than it is to
lose sensal Pleasures so like M you
would suffer more on average if you are
um engaged with sensuality than if
you're practicing like a good level of
self modification you would actually
suffer you your your your pleasure is
more impermanent if it depends on
Central Pleasures but when when when it
comes down to it both of them are
absolutely not ideal because both of
them are dependent on yeah on things
that are not in your control yeah
so um there's that Su that that talks
about the
the it's called the baits and it talks
about four types of deer herd yeah and
uh there's the first one who kind of
just carelessly goes into the to the
bait gets you know gets gets trapped by
the hunter yeah and then the hunter does
with them whatever he wants then there's
the other one who kind of recognizes
sees that the others are are falling
into the M on account of this and so
they decide to completely sh the bait
they go into the mountains and uh for
for a while they're free from the
trap but eventually uh there is no way
that they can stay there forever so
something will have to happen something
will have to
um prohibit the their their their
continual engagement in that practice so
they have to come back to where the the
bait was before and then because they
didn't learn how
to maneuver around the bait all they
know is the same old habit of biting
into it again and so they get caught the
the third one is um is a kind of a
settler problem that gets caught in
views we can discuss that later uh and
then only the fourth uh deer herd
knows how to stay where the hunt where
where the Trap is where the where the
hunter the in the range where the hunter
is setting straps but they have learned
how to not bite them so that's that's
that is like in a person who is
practicing the middle
way the difference is that they have
recognized that the baits are not
optional like
experiencing size sights sounds smells
tastes touches is not actually optional
whereas uh a person who is practicing
self modification is kind of having this
continuous Perpetual quest never- ending
quest to prevent themselves from
to prevent themselves from
experiencing um agreeable things and
that's that's impossible
because when you do that long enough
your avoidance of agreeable things
becomes agreeable so that's why it's like if you
agreeable so that's why it's like if you
you can never succeed in it without a
contradiction and the final point of
that is like you get to where the Buddha
actually went just before he kind of
turned around and realize that that was
the wrong path it's like I have to stop
breathing so as to truly not be
dependent on any kind of pleasure
because anything less than that if your
perception of of of uh Indulgence is
just the pleasure existing then the only
true way to kind of fulfill that ideal
is to go to that extreme like okay I
won't I won't even breathe now because
even that is is causing a form of
pleasure so that's why self mortification in the
so that's why self mortification in the
end is um is is futile
but it it uh it still has to like one
has to give things
up so it's not that that it's not that
one just oh I stay where I am and I just
abstractly think about the middle way
and uh that's how I I'm partaking the
Buddhist instruction there are factually
things that you have to give up like if
like I said before if you're not keeping
the precepts you have to take them on
you have to if you're not practicing
sense restraint you have to take take it
on
so like how would a person go
about um changing their behavior which
it nowadays is going to start from the
default point of indulgence yes so how
how do they kind
of um go about taking
on a closer version of the of the middle
way because another thing to not is that
the middle way is not a matter of choice
like often it's thought that the middle
way is just
about choosing kind of a intermediate
let's say let's say um I don't know
there's I have a choice between eating
very delicious food and then very
disagreeable food that tastes like paper
or something and I kind of choose
something in between and then that's the
middle way so like the middle as the Su
I just read says the middle way is the
noble for path and it starts with the
Right View meaning understanding the for
noral truths so the middle way can only
be practiced because the middle way is
the fourth Noel Truth by the way so it's
like only by knowing that truth that
that this is the middle way is the
person would be able to follow it so but
how does a person kind of set thems set
themselves up uh through the things that they can
up uh through the things that they can
do like the virtue and sense restraint
so that they do it more in the direction
of the middle way than
uh than aestheticism or self
modification why would they have to
[Music] um what would they as I said since
um what would they as I said since
externally it can look the same what is
it that internally they would have to do
so as to um not fall into that
trap well they need to know how to
attend to things rightly and based on
that um right
attention they will be able to
discern um whether they're acting out of
wholesome or UNH wholesome and then that
distinction might still be somewhat
blurred it will it will only be properly
clear once the view is right but that's
also not going to happen miraculously
that is sort of one needs to work on
that but our one is attending two things
which is the UN
that is going to be the factor there
that needs to be worked on in order for
the Noble 8-fold Path to become actual
human's experience yeah so yeah that is
there is actually one that I talked
about um how
the acquisition of
Y is like
the the the omen or the the the pance
for the arising of a nobody full path so
once a person
has understood that is basically the
understood that is basically the
condition and there's another another
one that
says and the utterance of another meaning you
and the utterance of another meaning you
know somebody who has understood the
dama uh is the uh are the two conditions
for the arising of the Right View
meaning the two conditions for the
arising of the no wful path MH so uh yes
that's true it's it's
y but how would you practice that
concretely uh because like for example
um you might
be like the the the the actual Middle
Way um as I was saying before it's not
it's not something that you can just fix
down as a code no that because sometimes
today doing one
thing will be rooted in Indulgence
tomorrow doing the same thing might be
rooted in self modification M based on
something that a person has to learn how
to
discern so as to start working on the
middle way so what is the thing yeah
yeah that is one's intentions yeah
behind one's actions like like why am I
doing this now am I doing this because I
want to avoid experiencing something
else or because I want to chase
something which I which I think I'm
lacking right now which is which is
already based on on on regarding things
wrongly um this whole notion of
something being missing right here and
now and to chase it um so then again
externally Behavior might look the same
but people might be doing it for
completely different let's say reasons
or or intentions and so that would be
the factor and an intention by the way
it's not publicly observable
behavior is what isly observable that is
what a scientist can study put a camera
there look at it from the outside but
why someone is doing what they're doing
that can at best be inferred and that's
and and it is impossible to to to
abandon doubt from the outside that can
only be done when one takes up this
first person present tense perspective
that's a sort of privileged point of
view where you see yourself doing what
you are doing while you doing it
including your reasons for doing it yeah
so so basically if you might be choosing
to not eat one day uhuh and based on the
intention behind that action that could
be either renunciation meaning the the
good sort of practice or it could be
self modification yeah so if
you're um
yeah so if there is an intention
regardless of what you tell yourself you
you might you know be 100% sure that
this is this practice according to
Buddhism and and but if the intention
behind the
action is affected with some type of
Desire some type of
craving no matter how
externally uh renunciates the action is
MHM it's leaning towards uh self
mortification so that's why actually
those two extremes they're not
like they are different only
superficially mhm in in in in their in
the depth of it they're exactly the same
they are craving for something that you
don't have right now yeah craving for
something outside of this this
experience mhm
so um so yeah the person that say
chooses not to eat
and that's because they have
this um ideal
of this Enlightenment that's going to
come to them that's kind of like okay
eventually I'm going to stop
experiencing uh these feelings that I
get when I fast eventually all this
stuff all this displeasure that I that I
experience right now is going to
disappear as a result of me just doing
this practice mhm and so
yeah exactly like you would see if that
person if something happens they can't
fast anymore uh some sort of circumstance
anymore uh some sort of circumstance
happens they would be annoyed internally
because they they're already uh kind of
setting their bets on this and it's it's
it's going to be unpleasant if it
doesn't go the way they want yeah so
it's it's uh it's still within like the
first Noble Truth getting what not
getting what you want and getting what
you don't want it's still revolving
around the same principle so then um but
if the person is let's say the intention
behind direction is not some kind of
desire for some experience or it's not
like um it's not this this uh
um it's not this this uh
external uh search for something else
it's more like you recognize that this
gives rise this practice
gives rise
to
um let's say certain me mental States
knowledge Vision as it is no no no get
gives R to wrong mental States like
let's say when you recognize yourself
that when you fast oh you have you know
the mind is revolving around it it's it
has complaints like it's it's it's um
you kind of it starts disturbing you and
it really puts you off your your mood
and that sort of stuff then if you take
that on as a form
on as a form
of
learning how not to Crave against
unpleasant feeling if if that is the intention
feeling if if that is the intention
behind your action then that
aestheticism externally what looks like
aestheticism could be beneficial but
even then it's not about just what you
state as your intention is not as about
what you would say if somebody asks you
what is your intention behind this
because that answer doesn't
change that that answer is going to be
the same all along but internally your
intention could switch back to desire at
any point M so and you might not be
aware of that yeah exactly so it's
knowing that intention has to be seen as
in turn as something internal not as
something that you just set once and
that's it like the intention doesn't
depend on you what what intention is
there right now the intention is like
basically the state of mind and the
State of Mind changes MH so that's what
you have to be aware of so if one day
you find yourself oh well I took the
practice of um fasting whatever I took
it initially as a genuine interest to um
learn how not to resist unpleasant
feeling and there was no kind of
external desire of wanting this this um
whatever subtle pleasure you might be
looking for that that that wasn't there
but then you see yourself oh but the
fasting itself doesn't hurt anymore the
mind is not really resisting it MH now
what the mind is resisting is not
getting this result out of the fasting
not getting this Enlightenment or
special Insight or whatever out of the
fasting then now that the displeasure
now moved the displeasure is you will
feel it if you stop fasting yeah because
now you you became attached to this so
then you would have to see oh so the
intention has changed yeah and then you
would have to uh adjust accordingly
so that's why there is no mechanical
guideline I just stick to this and then
you're going to be you're going to be
liberated even the the
most accurate instructions that you
might get from the Buddha himself you
might be applying them for the right
reasons for a time and then the
expectation sets in the craving sets in
and now you're going in the same
direction of of craving under the name
of dhama so it's like there is
nothing there are things that are always
wrong which is breaking the precepts mhm
but there is nothing that is always
right because the intention can always
be the intention behind behind the
practice can always be corrupted mhm and
ignore well ignore not seen and the
right practice is the intention behind
being right like the the right practice
is when when the intention behind what
you're doing is
right and that cannot be breaking the
precepts everything else if the
intention is right can be the right
practice so
um so how is somebody who is coming to
the practice recognizing that the middle
way is something one needs to acquire
right having said all of this now how is
somebody going to go about it if they
see the danger in Breaking precepts as
we've just said and there's the sensory
straint you can put on top of that
seclusion very beneficial suppose
somebody has no argumental cor with that
they they try to set that up to the best
of their
ability then what is that
it like like what's next and and
assuming that somebody is you know
taking advantage of the fact that the
discourses have been translated and all
sorts of languages take that on as a
mirror to learn about themselves
basically that materials there um then
then then what needs to happen next if
M's going to have a chance to gain the
Noble eful Path and then practice the
middleway well I think
practically it's uh like you might think
oh I'm restrained rightly and I I'm the
precepts rightly
rightly
but I think it's
very likely that you would do exactly
what you're just describing now so you
will take on the precepts you will take
on the Sens stength you will do this and
that the other failing to realize that
your intention
well maybe sometimes recognizing it but
not fully not always not not to the
sufficient degree that would what you call set this
degree that would what you call set this
bases up in the right way so
like yeah if you were to well yeah I
think if you were
to to do what you just described like
the giving the preset sens strain
seclusion always with the right
intention there's nothing else you need
to do exactly so the thing that you need
to constantly revise and revisit is okay
I should be doing these things why why
am I doing it right now like
not why it should be done but why am I
engaging in this right now and not in
that or why am I abstaining from the
other thing yeah so like basically you
you you hear what you have to do uh
based on the external instruction but
more important than just following the
external instruction is to constant
conly keep questioning what you're doing
because the because
um the mistake or the failure to have a
middle away is exactly what you said
it's not not even like you haven't
understood exactly what practice I need
to do it's more like when you do the
practices that that both and would be doing which
that that both and would be doing which
is very sense restraint and and and all
that um the the wrong intentions sneak
back in and you're kind
of likely very likely to not notice it
so that's that that is the most acute
thing like recognizing that you you
don't have the middle
way because you you you're not clear
about the intentions behind your actions
so for as long as you keep that in mind
you won't be taking you will stop
putting the emphasis on what practice I
do and what practice I don't do because
that's very clear already like if you're
self-honest the SS are very clear what
what practices sort of quotes should be
done uh so so you would just keep your
you you would just put your effort in
always being watchful of the intention
behind that practice because that's
what's going to determine um determine
it as being right or wrong so then
the middle way would become established
like the understanding of the
the yeah the foral truth would be when
you can't have the wrong intention
without realizing it when you can't kind
of accidentally slip into the wrong
reasons for doing the practice the wrong
reason for keeping the precepts the
wrong reason for for for being
restrained you can't be
um
accidentally um having a wrong intention
anymore that's when the middle way is
actually established so what makes it
what makes
it what what makes the ordinary
person uh not have a middle way is
just just that failure to see their own
intentions while they're there that's
why it's um the other
uh another way of describing what what
has to be seen in order to to get to get
the right view is what's called in the
Su is the sign of the
mind that that basically saying like the
mind is is the word mind chitt is um
ethologically connected to intention so
it's like a person who can't see their
intentions reliably is a person who won't be able
reliably is a person who won't be able
to
know what's wholesome as wholesome and
un wholesome as un wholesome meaning
they won't be able to know what is
according to the middle way and what
isn't so
um but then is it
like is it that you
are immediately able to see the full
extent of your intentions from the start
or is it like like should you be from
the very start
um really trying
to perfect your discernment of your
intentions in the to the maximum degree
so that you can just do the practice
or well I mean you can try it but that's
practically not how it's going to be
yeah
yeah so so yeah so when it starts with
precepts which means that you are
introducing some boundary to your
behavior this is this is where you're
going to see your intention you the
intention might still be there to go in
a certain direction and then you bump
into that precept so you are sort of in
that sense little bit divided against
yourself so to speak but that is
precisely showing you the problem and
and so that can be further refined which
allows less room for intentions to be
there without being seen rightly and
then you know with the Sens straint is
the same thing and and also seclusion is
going to reveal um like when one is
always surrounded by other people it's
very difficult to see that you might be
doing all sorts of things just you know
in know because I want to be understood
I want to be recognized I want to be
admired um I don't want to be rejected
but so so and those are those are this
type of intention behind actions yeah
but exactly and you're not going to see
any of that if you're always in that
same environment go and sit for a week
on your own without having anyone else
around or someone telling you what to do
and you can become very insecure because
suddenly is like oh there's no one here
actually acknowledging that I exist even
so now what I'm going to do and that
shows a whole side of the mind which is
in normal quote unquote circumstances
very difficult to see yeah it actually
says that without seeing the sign of the
Mind One can't get the right View and
then the sign of the Mind cannot be seen
in what is the lighting and
Company so that's actually a very good
example like cuz when we say intentions
behind actions it's not like um uh oh I
am doing this because tomorrow I have to
go to work and you know sleeping the
house today is necessary because I can't
do it tomorrow that that's not what it
means to say intention behind actions
intention behind action is on the level
of uh your attitude towards the feeling
so you could say there are if you want
to if you want to
um boil it down to the to the simplest
way there are three intentions behind
that actions only one of them is uh you
could say welcoming trying to get more
pleasure the other one is trying to get
less pain and the other one is trying to
distract yourself when there is neither
pleasure nor pain yeah so like like you
said when you're alone you're not
experiencing pleasure you're not
experiencing pain but there there will
still come this impulse to kind of for
the to get involved with something
because that kind of absence of of
something obvious to be preoccupied with
that becomes unpleasant yeah so
then those are the kind of intention
behind actions that one needs to be
looking for so there should be no
necessity for like a more uh super
detailed label of what the intention is
uh ra except those three that that
that's like you don't you don't need to
complicate it more than that mhm
so but the the point I was getting to
before was that yeah so it's not about
thinking that okay I'm going to figure
it out once and that's it I can see the
the intentions behind my actions now
there's multiple layers to it so there's
multiple layers to the middle way as
well like um the initially you will
be for example somebody who doesn't keep
the five precepts at all let's let's
take the the most extreme
case if they if they take on the five
precepts just taking on the five
precepts is going to be a form of them
seeing their intentions more MH than
they were doing before mhm like just
getting used to always keeping the five
precepts they will have to by necessity
have become more aware of their
intentions on a very basic level that's
not really enough with practice but kind
of M enough to to just not not
be like an animal um but they they will
have to become and that's exactly why uh
not keeping the five precepts is so bad
because it's
like completely just whatever intention
is there you just go with it MH so
that's why it's so bad but follow
keeping the five precepts at least will
force you that okay certain intentions
behind your actions you will not be able
to engage with anymore so when you see
those intentions you you won't do them
yeah so then that's one level then the next
so then that's one level then the next
level let's say you could you could say
the person takes on celibacy now that
will require a little bit more well
quite a bit more uh recognition of the
intention behind directions to to be
able to practically do it because you
can you can uh refrain from sexual
activity but uh your mind is going to
have those intentions there mhm because
it's used to go in that direction and
then if you don't recognize them you
will find your yourself sooner or later
about to engage in sex in sexual
activity so it will force you to
recognize the intentions behind your
actions as well and
uh it's just that that same it's that
progression so um from the beginning all
the way to the end it's just a
refinement of a person being able to see
uh the intentions behind your actions
more clearly in fact with the hindrances
when it comes to abandoning the
hindrances usually it's taken as it's
about focusing on objects and not
experiencing other objects uh anymore
but when the does explain what samadi is
it's always about purifying the Mind
from UNH wholesome things in the same
way that you are purifying your behavior
from un wholesome things from un
wholesome intentions so that's why in
fact there is no way for a person who
for a person to get somebody that is in
accordance with the middle way if they
haven't developed their body and
speech um in accordance with the middle
way beforehand because it's actually a
much subtler version of a more sub
subtler instance of the same principle
of purifying uh unhen intentions so
the're saying would would then uh the
the same thing that you did okay I
recognize this uh intention to do this
or that with my body I choose not to
engage with it well you would start to
see the same thing with your mind I see
a hindrance of sensuality I see a
hindrance of Will Will and obviously the
saying no to it is much coarser it's
much U it's done in on a much more
subtler level but it would be the same
as you choosing not to kill when there
is an intention to kill kill for example
so even that is also just about
intention behind dire actions there is
nothing nothing in the dharm that is
about something else like okay I watch
my intention Behind Act and then now
when it comes to samadi now it's time to
do something different MH so because
that's usually the perception and then
there there is no connection that
between your Sila and your Sam it's kind
of like just two different things
so um and then yeah once you start
seeing your intentions behind your
actions you recognize you are able once
you see them to a certain extent let's
say which is a sign of the Mind the
prerequisite for the Right View then you
can see oh these intentions are
suffering these intentions are the
origin of suffering so if I the
cessation of these intentions is the
sensation of
suffering so you will get to understand
the Four Noble Truths when you once you
are um to a very very high degree able
to see the intention behind your actions
mhm so
so
um yeah that that's like you
are fully established
in that principle of the middle way to
the point where now you can't forget it
anymore yeah for